Guide to the Federation of Houston Professional Women Records
University of Houston Libraries
Federation of Houston Professional Women Records
1981-2000
1998-006
Federation of Houston Professional Women
10.00 Linear Feet
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
The papers of the Federation of Houston Professional Women (FHPW) consist primarily of meeting notices, agendas, and minutes; fliers for Federation or Federation-sponsored activities; financial reports; membership rosters; and photographs. The majority of the material falls between 1990 and 1997.
Historical Note:
Throughout 1980, the various Houston area chapters of the American Business Women's Association gathered at quarterly "Community Meetings" in order to "exercise greater impact" through coordinated organization. In March 1981 these meetings opened to other Houston area women's groups. The overwhelming response of women throughout the city suggested a need to create an "umbrella" organization. From this effort sprang the Federation of Houston Professional Women (FHPW), established in September 1981, and chartered by the state of Texas in 1982. The FHPW would "help professional women serve as a resource to each other and to the community by providing educational, networking, and support group activities to its members, focus on empowering individuals to achieve their goals by addressing general concerns of women in civic, community, personal, and professional pursuits, and unite individuals of our member organizations to promote a place of influence and power." Together, the various groups involved in the Federation would attempt to educate women about the political process to foster activism that would create a more favorable environment for business women in Houston. (General FHPW information is found in Box 1, Folder 7).
As of 1994, the FHPW Foundation, Advisory Board, Executive Board, Board of Directors, several committees, and the voting delegates of the member organizations composed this "organization of organizations." Various prominent personalities from the Houston area sat on the Advisory Board. The Board of Directors included the Executive Board and the Directors of the various committees; the number and names of the committees have varied over the years. Until 1993, the FHPW published its news in the Federation Exchange. After 1993, the newsletter became known as the Federation Focus. A bulk mailing, the Delegate Digest, informed delegates of upcoming activities. Delegates kept their organizations informed about FHPW activities, and had voting privileges in Federation decisions.
Initially, the Federation planned four major activities: quarterly general meetings, a spring event, an annual awards banquet, and various workshops throughout the year. As the organization grew, the executive body and number of meetings multiplied. The FHPW continued to hold quarterly meetings open to all women involved in the Federation, as well as annual Delegate Updates to inform new voting delegates about their responsibilities and the FHPW's activities. The Executive Board and Board of Directors met monthly, as did several committees. The Awards Banquets in the autumn of each year continue to honor prominent and active women in Houston's business community. The Federation continues its educational outreach not only through workshops, but also through community service and the sponsorship of conferences promoting women in business and politics.
The FHPW's Educational Foundation was planned in 1993 with a mission to award scholarships and gifts to aid and advance the education and knowledge of women in the community. FHPWEF received tax-exempt status 501(c)3 in 1994 and as a charitable foundation is able to receive funds from contributions by individuals or member organizations, gifts, and special fundraisers. The Educational Foundation's Governing Board includes the FHPW's current president and president-elect. Five additional members are nominated by a committee consisting of the Educational Foundation's current president and the FHPW's current president and immediate past president. The Educational Foundation's voting body is the Governing Board and the FHPW Board of Directors.
Access Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Corporate Name:
Federation of Houston Professional Women
Genre/Form of Material:
Fliers (printed matter); Minutes; Photographs; Records (documents)
Topical Term:
Business networks -- Texas -- Houston; Businesswomen -- Texas -- Houston; Women -- Societies and clubs -- Texas -- Houston; Women in the professions
Acquisition Information:
Donation by the Federation of Houston Professional Women, 1998 and 2002.
Conditions Governing Access:
Open for research.
Scope and Contents
The papers of the Federation of Houston Professional Women (FHPW) consist primarily of meeting notices, agendas, and minutes; fliers for Federation or Federation-sponsored activities; financial reports; membership rosters; and photographs. The majority of the material falls between 1990 and 1997. The collection does, however, contain the minutes of the original meeting of the FHPW in 1981. Member organization rosters give researchers an impression of women's business and professional activities throughout the Houston area in the 1980s and 1990s.
The records are arranged into four series: Administration, Events, FHPW Educational Foundation, and Mixed Media. The original organization of the records varied according to president. Usually it was chronological by year, topical within each year, then chronological within each topic. Material from the earliest years was interspersed throughout the different series. The current organization was imposed upon the collection to standardize the filing, and to integrate the years.
Detailed List of Contents
- Administration
  This series contains material pertaining to the administrative activities of the FHPW. It has been divided into five sub-series: Organizations, Boards, Committees, Financial, and Delegates. The majority of the items concern meetings of various boards and committees.
  - Organization
    This sub-series consists of administrative material pertaining to the history of the FHPW, including correspondence and legal documents, dating from 1981 to 1999. It is arranged alphabetically.
    - By-Laws and Articles of Incorporation, 1982-1997 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Calendars, 1981-1999 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Call Logs, 1998-1999 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, 1985-1994 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, 1996-1999 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Job Descriptions, 1996-1997 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - History, 1981-1993 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Newspaper Clippings, 1987-1996 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Policy and Procedures Manual, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Proclamations, 1992, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Stationery, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Boards
    This sub-series contains thirteen folders, dating from 1981 to 1999, arranged alphabetically. The majority of the material pertains to the activities of the Board of Directors, and includes notices, agendas, and minutes for the Board and Executive meetings. The meeting minutes of the Board of Directors and the Executive Board have been interfiled chronologically.
    - Advisory, 1989-1996 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Board of Directors and Executive Board, 1981-1987 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Board of Directors and Executive Board, 1988-1990 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Board of Directors and Executive Board, 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Board of Directors and Executive Board, 1994-1995 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Board of Directors and Executive Board, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Board of Directors and Executive Board, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 18-19)
    - Board of Directors and Executive Board, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 20-21)
    - Board of Directors and Executive Board, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Rosters, 1986-1993 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Rosters, 1993-1999 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Committees
    This sub-series contains fifteen folders, dating from 1982-1999 and is arranged alphabetically, concerning the various committees that report to the FHPW Board of Directors.
    - Ambassador, 1996-1997 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - By-Laws, 1988-1999 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Civics Projects, 1986-1999 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Civics Projects, Classy Clown Corps, 1994-1998 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Communication, 1984-1997 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Credit Union, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Database, 1988-1999 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Education, 1987-1997 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Internet, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Long-Range Planning, 1987-1996 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Membership, 1987-1999 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Nominating, 1982-1996 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Program, 1988-1999 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Speakers Bureau, 1982-1996 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Ways and Means, 1988-1999 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Financial
    This sub-series of twelve folders comprises the group's financial records from 1982-1999. Most of the material consists of Treasurer's Reports.
    - Audits, 1982, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Credit Cards, 1993, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Dues Reports/Membership, 1983-1999 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Income Tax Information, 1985-1990 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Treasurer's Report, 1986-1989 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Treasurer's Report, 1992-1993 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Treasurer's Report, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Treasurer's Report, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Treasurer's Report, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Treasurer's Report, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Treasurer's Report, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Treasurer's Report, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Delegates
    This sub-series of twenty folders dates from 1981 to 2000, and contains material regarding delegates to the FHPW. The Delegate Digest was a monthly mailing of fliers intended to keep delegates from the member organizations informed about FHPW activities. The Quarterly General Meetings information, consisting of notices, agendas, and minutes, was sent to delegates in packet form.
    - Delegate Digest, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Delegate Digest, 1990-1991 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Delegate Digest, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Federation Exchange, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Information Packets, 1985-1997 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Focus, 1993-1994 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Focus, 1995-1997 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Focus, 1998-1999 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Member Roster, 1981-1984 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Member Roster, 1985-1989 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Member Roster, 1992-1994 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Member Roster, 1995-1996 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Member Roster, 1997-1998 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Member Roster, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Quarterly General Meetings, 1981-1984 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Quarterly General Meetings, 1987-1990 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Quarterly General Meetings, 1992-1997 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Quarterly General Meetings, 1998-2000 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Update, 1984-1998 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - VIP, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Events
  This series concerns the activities and events sponsored by the FHPW. It is divided into two sub-series: Awards Banquet and Programs and Workshops. These contain fliers, programs, and paperwork pertaining to the many events sponsored by the FHPW.
  - Awards Banquet
    This sub-series is arranged chronologically and contains material regarding the annual awards banquet, the FHPW's largest annual event.
    - 1982-1987 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - 1988-1990 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - 1991-1992 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - 1993 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - 1994 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - 1994 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - 1995 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - 1996 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - 1997-1998 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - 1999 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - 2000 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - 2001 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Programs and Workshops
    This sub-series contains eleven folders dating from 1981-1994, arranged in chronological order.
    - Miscellaneous, 1981-1993 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Miscellaneous, 1994-1997 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - A Quality You, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Team Politics in Organizations, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Garage Sale, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Logo Contest, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Women of the 90s, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - The Women's Event, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Visions, the Women's Expo, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Houston Women's Show, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Houston International Festival, 1994 (Box 5, Folder 11)
- FHPW Educational Foundation
  This series consists of the records of the FHPW Educational Foundation. Materials consist primarily of event records and scholarship applications, with the majority dating from 1995 to 1998 and a small amount from before 1995. The series also contains minutes, logos, and mission statements. This series is arranged into three sub-series: Administration, Scholarships, and Events.
  - Administration
    This sub-series contains six folders pertaining to the administrative of the Educational Foundation.
    - Correspondence, 1996-1997 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Financial, 1996-2000 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Governance Documents, 1994-1998 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Governing Board, 1994-2000 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Minutes, 1994-2000 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Miscellaneous, 1996-1997 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Scholarships
    This sub-series contains scholarship applications pre-dating the formation of the Educational Foundation, as well as material from after its creation. The records consist primarily of applications and correspondence related to scholarships. Additionally, the series includes sample application forms, rules governing the application and scholarship awarding process, and background research conducted about other organizations that had similar scholarship schemes.
    - Applications, 1988-1996 (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Applications, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Applications, 1998-1999 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Background Research, 1993-1998 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - Outside Sources, 1994-1997 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Events
    The seven folders in this sub-series contain material regarding the Educational Foundation's events. The Alley shows were of significance since they were the prime fundraisers for the foundation, which awarded scholarships from these funds.
    - Alley Theatre, 1995-1997 (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - Alley Theatre, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - Alley Theatre, 1999-2000 (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - Coffee, Tea and Italia, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 26)
    - Coffee, Tea and Italia, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 27)
    - Galveston Summer Musical, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 28)
    - Ideahouse Grand Revue and Tour, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 29)
- Audiovisual, Photographs, and Slides
  This series contains photographs, slides, and different kinds of tapes. The series is divided into two sub-series: Photographs and Slides, and Tapes. The three audio tapes mainly concern FHPW orientations. The magnetic tapes contain records of FHPW logos, mission statements, awards banquet meeting minutes, and Board minutes. The videotapes are of awards banquets.
  - Photographs and Slides
    This sub-series of thirty-four folders contains photographs, slides and negatives dating from 1984-1995. It is divided into three sub-sub-series: events, meetings, and people. Included are photos taken during awards banquets and rehearsal tea parties, as well as official headshots of the honorees.
    - Events
      - Awards Banquet, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 1)
      - Awards Banquet, 1985 (Box 6, Folder 2)
      - Awards Banquet, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 3)
      - Awards Banquet Rehearsal Tea, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 4)
      - Awards Banquet, 1992 (Box 6, Folder 5-7)
      - Awards Banquet, 1993 (Box 6, Folder 8-9)
      - Awards Banquet, 1994 (Box 6, Folder 10)
      - Awards Banquet Rehearsal Tea, 1995 (Box 6, Folder 11)
      - Awards Banquet, 1996 (Box 6, Folder 12)
      - Awards Banquet, undated (Box 6, Folder 13)
      - Exhibit, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 14)
      - Miscellaneous, 1984-1986 (Box 6, Folder 15)
      - 10th Anniversary - Slides, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 16-17)
      - Awards - Slides, 1993 (Box 6, Folder 18)
      - Federation Exchange - Slides, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Meetings
      - Delegate Update, 1985-1986 (Box 6, Folder 20)
      - General, 1985 (Box 6, Folder 21)
      - General, January 1986 (Box 6, Folder 22)
      - Historian Committee, 1986 (Box 6, Folder 23)
      - Miscellaneous, 1990's (Box 6, Folder 24)
    - People
      - Honorees - Slides, 1982 (Box 6, Folder 25)
      - Honorees - Slides, 1983 (Box 6, Folder 26)
      - Honorees - Slides, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 27)
      - Honorees - Slides, 1985 (Box 6, Folder 28)
      - Honorees - Slides, 1994 (Box 6, Folder 29)
      - Honorees - Slides, 1995 (Box 6, Folder 30)
      - Honorees - Slides, 1996 (Box 6, Folder 31)
      - Honorees - Slides, 2001 (Box 6, Folder 32)
      - Members - Slides, 1994 (Box 6, Folder 33)
      - Miscellaneous, 1984-1990 (Box 6, Folder 34)
  - Tapes
    This sub-series is divided into three sub-sub-series: Audio, Magnetic, and Video, dated 1993-1999. The three audio tapes mainly have the federation orientations. The magnetic tapes contain records of federation logos, mission statements, awards banquet meeting minutes, and federation board meeting minutes. The videotapes are of awards banquets and the opening of the federation.
    - Audio
      - FHPW, 1987 (Box 7, Item 1)
      - Federation Orientation (Old), undated (Box 7, Item 2)
      - Federation Orientation, undated (Box 7, Item 3)
    - Magnetic
      - FHPW Logo/Statements, undated (Box 7, Item 4)
      - Awards Banquet, 1997 (Box 7, Item 5)
      - Awards Banquet, Focus, 1997 (Box 7, Item 6)
      - Minutes, 1997 (Box 7, Item 7)
      - Board Meeting, 1998 (Box 7, Item 8)
    - Video
      - Awards Banquet, 1987 (Box 7, Item 9)
      - Awards Banquet, 1990 (Box 7, Item 10)
      - Awards Banquet, 1991 (Box 7, Item 11)
      - Awards Banquet, 1993 (Box 7, Item 12)
      - Awards Banquet, 1994 (Box 7, Item 13)
      - Awards Banquet, 1996 (Box 7, Item 14)
      - Awards Banquet, 1998 (Box 7, Item 15)
      - Awards Banquet, 1999 (Box 7, Item 16)
      - Rehearsal Tea, 1997 (Box 7, Item 17)
      - Federation Opening, undated (Box 7, Item 18)
      - Untitled, undated (Box 7, Item 19)
- Oversize
  materials from several different series are resprented in this oversize box
  - Miscellaneous (Ovs box 1, Ovs item 1)